Guide to the Morris Cooper Foote Papers M2103
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Morris Cooper Foote papers
1886-1913
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Foote, Morris Cooper, 1843-1905
M2103
3 Linear Feet (4 boxes, 2 map folders)
The papers of Morris Cooper Foote document his career in the United States Army during the Boxer Rebellion in Northern China and the Spanish-American War in Cuba.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Foote Biography
Morris Cooper Foote was born September 16, 1843, at Madison Barracks, Sackett’s Harbor, New York, to Lyman and Mary M. (Cooper) Foote. His great-grandfather was William Cooper, the founder of Cooperstown, New York, and his maternal great-grandfather was Jacob Morris, who served as an officer in the Revolutionary War, whose father was Lewis Morris, a signer of the Declaration of Independence. Foote was also the great-nephew of novelist James Fenimore Cooper. After his father died during the Mexican War in 1846 his mother moved to Cooperstown with her children. Foote attended school here for a time, later going to Plattsburg and to a Commercial College in Syracuse.
Foote enlisted in the New York Volunteer Infantry in 1861, beginning a forty year military career. He served throughout the entire Civil War, and was present at the surrender of Lee at Appomattox. He was captured in April 1864 at Plymouth, North Carolina and was held was a prisoner at Libby, Macon, Charleston and Columbia, escaping from the latter and taking refuge on board the U. S. gunboat Nipsic. In December 1864, he was among the 600 officer prisoners of war placed under fire in an effort to prevent the batteries on Morris Island from shelling the city of Charleston. He was the only officer hit, receiving a slight flesh wound from a piece of shell. Foote published a memoir based on his Civil War experiences.
After the Civil War, Foote served with his regiment in California, Alaska, Nevada, Arizona, New Mexico, South Dakota, Colorado, Wyoming and Nebraska. He commanded one of the two companies of the 9th U.S. Infantry that received the Territory of Alaska from Russia in 1867, and was present when the Russian flag was hauled down at Sitka.
He was adjutant of the Black Hills Expedition under Col. Richard I. Dodge in 1875, and was in charge at the Brule Sioux Indian Agency the next year. He served in the field against the Sioux in 1877 and in the Geronimo Campaign in 1886, witnessing Geronimo’s surrender to General Miles at Skeleton Canyon, Arizona.
At the beginning of the Spanish-American War, Foote went to Cuba with the 9th U.S. Infantry, commanded a battalion at San Juan, and was at the surrender of the Spanish Army in the city of Santiago in July 1898. The following month Foote received promotion to the rank of Major and was ordered to Boston for recruiting duty, being unable to rejoin his regiment at the time due to malaria.
In June 1900 Foote went to the Philippine Islands but was soon on his way to northern China with his regiment. China’s Boxer Rebellion was an anti-foreign peasant uprising that had begun to escalate in the northern coastal province of Shandong. Hundreds of Orthodox, Protestant and Catholic missionaries and many more Christian Chinese were massacred. The movement also resisted growing imperialist tendencies in the area by European, Russian and American powers.
On June 17, the Boxers (also known as Yihetuan, or “Militia United in Righteousness”) began a siege of the Legation Quarter in Peking, where many foreigners and Christians were sequestered. The United States, along with Great Britain, Russia, Germany, France, Italy and Japan conducted a military expedition for the relief of the legations, sending 5000 troops for the purpose. The international relief expedition, known as the Eight-Nation Alliance, marched from Taku to Tientsin, and then the seventy more miles to Peking, raising the siege on August 4th. Foote was also present at the Battle of Tientsin, where the 9th infantry suffered a ten percent casualty rate. Negotiations following the defeat of the Boxers allowed for various foreign powers to administrate in certain territories, and in October 1900 Foote was ordered to return to Tientsin in command of United States forces. He also represented the United States in the Tientsin Provisional Government, known as the “Conseil du Governement Provisiors de Tientsin.”
Foote returned with his regiment to the Philippines in May 1901 and served at Basey, Samar, for some months. Later, as Colonel of the 28th U.S. Infantry, he served in Cavite Province, near Manila, and also on the Island of Mindanao.
After being appointed a Brigadier General on February 18, 1903, Foote retired the following day. He moved to Europe and resided in Geneva, Switzerland for two years. At the Hotel d'Angleterre, after recovering from double pneumonia and double pleurisy, he passed away of heart failure on December 6, 1905. He is buried at Arlington National Cemetery.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Morris Cooper Foote (1843-1905) document the latter part of his career in the United States Army, especially his service in Cuba during the Spanish-American War and in China during and after the Boxer Rebellion. Foote’s papers consist of over 300 items, including manuscripts, journals, diaries, correspondence, official reports and documents, photographs, maps, newspapers, printed ephemera, and related material. Extensive notes and transcriptions were made prior to accession; some copies of which are filed in the collection.
During the Spanish-American War, Foote commanded a battalion on San Juan Hill with Theodore Roosevelt’s “Rough Riders” and others. The collection includes Foote’s eyewitness account of the action. Foote was also stationed at various times in the Philippines, and there are some photographs and correspondence from the Islands. The bulk of the archive contains manuscript, photographic, cartographic, and ephemeral material documenting Foote’s service in Northern China following the Boxer Rebellion, with his regiment, the 9th Infantry, during the China Relief Expedition at Tientsin (the nearest port city to Peking, presently Tianjin), and Peking (presently Beijing).
Foote was commander of American forces at Tientsin, and was also the United States Representative of the Provisional Government of that city. Correspondents during this time include Major General Adna R. Chaffee, Chief Secretary Charles Denby Jr., and Adjutant General Henry Hiestand of the China Relief Expedition Headquarters in Peking, as well as communication from Allied Supreme Commander Alfred von Waldersee. There is also a small amount of correspondence and other material about his family and various financial investments.
China -- History -- Boxer Rebellion, 1899-1901 -- Campaigns; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Campaigns -- Cuba; Foote, Morris Cooper, 1843-1905; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 9th (1855-1957)
- General Orders and Circulars, War Department; Personal and Post Orders, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Two binders of Army orders as bound by Foote.
- Private Journal, 5/1/1896 - 10/20/1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Text of private journal [transcription], 5/1/1896 - 10/20/1900 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Private Journal, 1/1/1886 - 4/30/1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Text of private journal [transcription], 1/1/1886 - 14/30/1896 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
- Correspondence to Foote re: investments, stock certificate, etc., 1888-1894 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes letter from Foote's son Francis, biographical notes on Peter Cooper, and other items.
- Notes for and draft of account of military service, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Individual service report, Manila, 6/30/1898 - 6/30/1900 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Individual service report, Boston, 6/30/1897 - 6/30/1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Paper on Santiago Campaign and on Regular troops as compared to National Guard, 1899-08 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Orders of Foote's transfer from Manila to Taku, China and four receipts, 1900-06-29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Retained copy of Foote's report of the Battle of Tientsin, 1900-07-14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Retained copy of supplementary report, Tientsin, 1900-07-25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Two telegraph receipts, 1900-07-31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Manuscript orders from Headquarters, Foote ordered to Tong Chow, China Relief Expedition, 1900-08-19 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- General Orders No. 10, China Relief Expedition, Peking, 1900-08-26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- General Orders No. 11, China Relief Expedition, Peking, 1900-08-28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- E.H. Conger note to Foote, 1900-09-06 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- General Orders No. 16, China Relief Expedition, Peking, 1900-09-09 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Special Orders No. 60, China Relief Expedition, Peking: Foote to Tientsin, 1900-10-16 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Proposals for the Council, outline of districts of the Conseil (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Lists of officers, roster of troops, commissioners, ordnance and explosives, Tientsin and Peking, 12/25/1900 - 2/5/1901 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Denby to Foote re: rice distribution [undated, probably November 1900]; Financial statement of Tientsin Provisional Government, 1900-10-31 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Draft of Proposed Regulations For The Conveyance of Land in Tientsin Provisional Government Jurisdiction and related, 1900-11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Text in English and French. Contains notes, memoranda and proposals made by various members of the Provisional Government, including Mr. Emens, Mr. Rump, and Baron Gunzburg.
- District of Tientsin General Rules of Administration (Box 2, Folder 1)
- General Chaffee, China Relief Expedition Headquarters letter to Foote regarding council of provisional government, 1900-11-02 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Denby letter to Foote re: Provisional Government officers, Tientsin, 1900-11-13 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Drafts of Foote letters re: Provisional Government; New Regulations for the district; structure of government, 1900-11-14 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Lewis R. Tucker personal letter to Foote, 1900-11-16 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Provisional Government of Tientsin Native City reports, 11-12/1900 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Includes reports from the Chief Secretary's Department, Treasury, Judicial Department, Chinese Secretary's Office, and Public Works Department.
- Adjutant General Hiestand, China Relief Expedition Headquarters, Peking letter to Foote re: loan to Provisional Government, 1900-11-20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Allied Supreme Commander Waldersee letter re: improvements to Peiho River, English translation, 1900-1901 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- General Chaffee, China Relief Expedition Headquarters, Peking letter to Provisional Council re: proposed changes to regulations, 1900-12-8 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- [British Army Captain Gerald Francis] Mockler letter to Foote in San Francisco with news from Tientsin, 1900-11-17 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Roster of Allied Troops in Province of Pe-Chili, Army headquarters in East Asia, Winter Palace, Peking, 1900-12-11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Roster of Officers and Troops, China Relief Expedition, 1900-12-1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- List of Ammunition etc. Sold to Messrs. Arnold Karberg & Co. From City Arsenal (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Adjutant General Hiestand, China Relief Expedition Headquarters, Peking letter to Foote with enclosed letter in English translation from Field Marshal Waldersee to General Chaffee re: Tientsin Provisional Government, 1900-12 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Telegrams from Chaffee and Heistand to Foote (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Military Order of the Dragon documents, 1900-1901 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  "At meetings of the officers of the U.S. Forces, Peking, China, October 1st, 2nd and 3rd, 1900, a society known as 'The Military Order of the Dragon' was organized."
- Statement of Strength of U.S. Forces in China, 1900-02-01 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Receipts: Tientsin Club, Provisional Government Mess, Otsego Lodge, etc., 1901 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- James W. Ragsdale, U.S. Consulate, Tientsin letter to Foote re: United States Concession in Tientsin, 1900-02-27 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Ernest B. Barrat letters to Foote, 2-4/1901 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Receipts: Provisional Government Mess, etc., 2-3/1901 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Charles D. Jameson (American Society of Civil Engineers) invitation to Foote, 1901-04-03 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Letter to Pastors Wan and Ming in English translation, re: China, Boxers, etc., 1901 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Enclosed envelope addressed to Col. Foote has inscription "D.E. Smith letters"
- General Chaffee, China Relief Expedition Headquarters, Peking letter to Foote re: corruption in Provisional Government, 1901-04-02 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- General Chaffee, China Relief Expedition Headquarters, Peking letter to Foote: follow up to last letter about corruption, 1901-04-11 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Gouvernement Provisoire du District de Tientsin letter to Foote with enclosed memo from Chinese Secretary's Office regarding wage scale for Chinese employees, 1901-04-10 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Receipt for Pommard [Burgundy wine] paid by Foote to James Hirsbrunner, 1901-04-16 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Related Materials
  There is an advertisement for Hirsbrunner in the Peking & Tientsin Times newspaper in map-folder 4.
- James W. Ragsdale, U.S. Consulate letter to Foote in Manila re: banner of appreciation from village outside Tientsin, 1901-07-20 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- A. Shaw letter to Foote, 1901-02-28 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- H. Bower letter to Foote, 1901-04-08 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Major General George Davis to General Henry C. Corbin re: Foote's retirement, Manila, 1903-01-22 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Adjutant General Heistand telegram to Foote re: promotion, 1903-02-18 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Pocket notebook (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Notebook with notes on Cuba, China, retirement, 1898-1904 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Includes journal entries, letter drafts, inventories, calculations, etc.
- Telegrams to and from Annie Foote, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  35 telegrams and their receipts from Foote to his wife Annie Elizabeth Murphy Foote in San Francisco, as well as some sent in return.
- Private journal, 8/1/1903 - 11/29/1905 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Foote passed away a week after the last entry. Journal has some clippings, receipts, and a telegram inserted in the unused portion.
- Text of private journal, Morris C. Foote Brig. Gen. U.S. Army [transcription], 8/1/1903 - 11/29/1905 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Includes letter from Foote to his wife Annie 4/1898; J.L. Pierson to Foote 11/29/1903; Sarah Pike Conger, U.S. Legation, Peking invitation [undated]; Foote's children Cooper and Francis to Foote 1901; Herman Ridder to Annie Foote 1/18/1912 re: bond investment
- E.C. Bumpus letter to Foote re: his son First Lieutenant Edward A. Bumpus' death at Balangiga, 1901-10-07 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Visiting cards, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  17 calling cards and one printed invitation. Includes those of many of Foote's colleagues on the Provisional Government, as well as Major Erich von Falkenhayn, future chief of German General Staff during World War One.
- General Orders No. 32 and No. 37, Ninth Infantry Headquarters, Calbayog, Samar, Philippine Islands, 10-11/1901 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  General Orders No.32 concerns the attack on the 9th Infantry at Balangiga [often called the Balangiga Massacre, although the reprisal attacks by the U.S. Army are also known by that name]
- Letters, telegram, etc. re: Foote's promotion and retirement, 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Foote to Adjutant General 12/25/1902 re: promotion and retirement; H.S. Hull, War Department letter to Annie Foote 12/31/1902; program for band concert honoring Foote 2/23/1903; telegram ordering General Foote to Manila 2/23/1903
- Correspondence, etc., 1901-1913 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Includes letters and related re: Oakwood Park stock farm in Contra Costa County 5/24/1901; letter from G.P. Reese, Cooperstown to Annie Foote [undated]; Furlough Songs Of The Class of 1913 [printed songbook]
- Reglements generaux d'administration de la cite chinoise de Tientsin. Tientsin Press, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  Printed rules for the administration of Tientsin.
- de Linde, A., Report of the Hai-Ho River Improvement And The Rivers of Chihli (Reprinted From Report of 1890). Tientsin Press, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- de Linde, A., Rapport Sur Les Travaux D' Amelioration Dans La Riviere du Hai-Ho. Tientsin Press, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Appendix to Army Regulations, Edition of 1901, Showing Changes to December 31, 1902, and Orders and Circulars Relating Thereto (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States Circular No. 34, in Memoriam Morris Cooper Foote, 1906-9-10 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Waeber, Ch., Map of North Eastern China, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Four folded cloth-backed maps of northeastern China published in Hamburg by L. Friederichson and Co.
- Map of North Eastern China, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Folded cloth-backed map of northeastern China published in Washington, D.C. by the Adjutant-General's Office, Military Information Division.
- Hermann, M., Reisekarte von Mittel-Europa [map of Middle Europe]. Glogau: Carl Flemming Verlag, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Zones Internationales dans le Pei-Cho-Lil [map], circa 1900 (Box 5, Item 1)
  Blue-print map measuring approx. 12"x12" showing the International concessions in the vicinity of Tientsin and Peking. Rail lines and rivers are outlined. Probably produced in the field by French engineers for the use of Allied forces.
- Tientsin to Peking China [map], 1900 (Map-folder 6)
  Blue-print map measuring 29.5" x 12.5" showing route of U.S. troops in the China Relief Expedition, August 4-14, 1900.
- Cyanotype group portrait of seventeen Allied soldiers of various nationalities, possibly in Tientsin (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photographs of beheading of two Chinese men in Tientsin (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Series of nine prints measuring 3x4 inches documenting the execution of two Chinese men in a street in Tientsin before a crowd of Chinese civilians and Allied soldiers.
- Photograph of company of Bengal Lancers escorting Count Waldersee on his arrival at Peking, before the Sacred Gate [Underwood & Underwood stereoview], 1901 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Mounted cabinet image of unidentified steamship [stamped Nippon Artistmade Photograph] (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series of seven photographs of Malabon, Philippines by J.M. Shera (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Group portrait of members of Tientsin Provisional Government, circa 1900 (Box 5, Items 2-6)
  Five versions of the same photograph, one signed by all members and another reproducing the photo with the signatures. Mounts are credited to Yamamoto (Tokyo) and J.D. Givens (San Francisco).
- Studio portrait of eleven China Relief Expedition officers, circa 1900 (Box 5, Item 7)
  Mount indicates photographer Sanyu & Co., Tientsin. Officers are identified on verso.
- Newspaper clippings, notes, envelopes, handwritten Chinese documents (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Japanese print with text (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Ordre du Double Dragon, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Book with text in Chinese and French and drawings of insignia. No publisher noted. Inscribed by Foote in Tientsin July 14th, 1900.
- Description from source of archive (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Detailed notes on the collection, including many transcriptions (copies of some are also filed with original documents).
- Newspapers, 1887-1905 (Map-folder 4)
  Otsego Journal Vol.12 No. 9 6/22/1887; Boston Globe 5/23/1899 [one sheet with article on Foote]; Peking and Tienstin Times Vol.7 No. 48 4/6/1901; New York Herald, European Edition 12/8/1905 [obituary]; Journal De Geneve No. 336 12/8/1905 [short obituary]